This is a robot that walks,
这是一个可以走
flies,
可以飞
skateboards,
可以玩滑板
and slacklines.
还能走钢丝的机器人
But why?
为啥
There are lots of bipedal robots out there,
早就有很多两脚机器人了
and drones are ubiquitous.
而且无人机也无处不在
But until now, no one had engineered
然而直到现在  仍然没有人
walking and flying technology to work together
将行走和飞行两项技术
in a single robot.
共同搭载在同一台机器人上
- So it's the first robot that truly integrates
- 因此这是第一台
the walking and the flying.
不仅能走还能飞的机器人
It's not just a drone with legs.
它可不只是个有两条腿的无人机
- [Dr. Chung] It's LEONARDO and it stands for
- [Chung博士] 这是LEONARDO
LEgs ONboARD drOne.
代表“带腿的无人机”
So I think it's a pretty good name.
我觉得是个好名字
- [Derek] Why is this potentially useful?
- [Derek] 为啥这腿有可能会很有用
- Yeah, so any flying vehicles
- 每一台飞行器
actually have to start from the ground to take off.
实际上都是从地面起飞
And eventually, they can not stay in the air forever.
并且它们不可能永远停留在空中
They have to eventually come down.
它们最终都得降落
But sometimes they have to come down
但有些时候
on the very challenging terrain or some obstacles.
它们得在一些奇怪的地形或者障碍上降落
So it's actually a good idea to have
所以给它们装上这些可以动的腿
these controlLable legs.
是个不错的主意
So they can actually land
然后它们就可以
in a very interesting configuration,
以一些奇怪的姿态
or posture, or orientation.
或者方向来进行降落
- [Derek] But there are additional benefits.
- [Derek] 但是这两条腿还有一些其他的好处
A robot like this is more stable than a regular drone.
一台这样子的机器人比常见的无人机更加稳定
- I view these propellers almost like arms.
- 我感觉这些螺旋桨看起来就像胳膊一样
So some people might say that,
所以有些人可能会说
oh, you guys are cheating because I mean,
噢  你们开挂了吧
bipedal robots do not have propellers,
两足机器人怎么能有螺旋桨嘞
but we are essentially using the propellers
但这些螺旋桨
to do additional stabilization.
实际上只是用来提供额外的稳定性
(robot whirring)
（机器人嗡嗡）
So basically, you generate the lift or thruster force
简单来说  我们通过产生向上的推力
to cancel some of the the weight of the robot,
来抵消机器人受到的部分重力
but that's really a secondary factor.
但这是次要的
The most important thing is basically
实际上  最重要的是
posture or orientation, stabilization.
稳定的姿态和方向
(robot whirring)
（机器人嗡嗡）
- [Derek] That is so cool to see.
- [Derek] 真棒
- So the main facility for this lab
- 这间实验室的主要设施
is this one.
是这个
It's a gigantic fan array.
这是个巨大的风扇阵列
- [Derek] I can see all the fans now.
- [Derek] 我可以看到所有的风扇
- [Dr. Chung] Yeah, we have - you can start counting,
- [Chung博士] 确实  你可以数数
but 1,296 computer fans.
一共有1296个电脑风扇
Those are really literally computer fans.
这些就是字面意思上的电脑风扇
- [Derek] How fast can it generate wind?
- [Derek] 他们可以产生多大的风
- So up to 15 meters per second or 20 meters per second.
- 最大风速15米/秒到20米/秒
- [Derek] It's like a wind tunnel
without the need for a tunnel.
- [Derek] 风 洞 没 有 洞 ？
- Yes.
- 确实
- It might mess with our audio or with our microphones.
- 它可能会把我们的音频搞得乱七八糟
Whoa.
哇哦
- The idea of the smoke machines
- 这些烟雾机的主要作用
is to actually visualize the flow,
就是让我们能够看见气流
but also with all these additional sensors,
并且加上这些额外的传感器
like infrared cameras or radar and LIDAR,
比如红外摄像头和激光雷达
how we can actually figure out the kind of location
让我们可以在这种有雾的情况下
or environment around your vehicle
能够确定无人机的位置
in the presence of this fog.
或确定周围的环境
- [Derek] I wanted to feel their power for myself.
- [Derek] 我想感受一下这散热器阵列的力量
- [Man] All right, you ready?
- [那个男人] 好的  你准备好了么
- [Derek] Yeah, let's do it.
- [Derek] 来吧
(machine whirring loudly)
（机器巨大的嗡嗡声）
Yeah!
耶
That was so cool.
这东西太炫酷了
I love it.
我喜欢这个
They use this facility to test Leonardo
他们用这东西来测试Leonardo
to see how stable he is even in different wind conditions.
看看它在不同风速下的稳定性如何
(orchestral music)
（管弦乐）
- And we showed that Leo is more robust than a drone
- 我们证明了Leo比无人机更强壮
because a drone gets blown away by the wind.
因为无人机会被风吹走
But then Leo does not because of its ground contact.
但Leo不会  因为它“触地”了
So for example, if you go hiking and there's like,
举个栗子  比如你去远足
suddenly a lot of wind, you're not gonna fall
然后突然一阵大风吹过  你并不会摔一跤
because you have the ground contact.
因为你接触到了地面
But for a drone, it might be blown away.
但如果是个无人机  它可能就被吹走了
(gentle soft orchestra music)
（柔和的管弦乐）
(robot whirring)
（机器人嗡嗡）
- [Man] Oh no.
- [那个男人] 噢不
- So we actually took one of the whiteboards
that we have at home and we put oil.
So we applied perturbations to Leo,
and what's happening is as you push Leo, instead of falling,
it stays upright, but it also slides on the white board.
So that's an interesting capability.
So it's very robust.
- You said perturbations.
Are you poking the robot?
- Yes, without harming the robot.
We are gentle.
(robot whirring)
- LEONARDO is so stable and good at adjusting its balance,
that it can skateboard.
(robot whirring)
That's a fancy trick.
Not many people can go backwards on a skateboard.
How did you get the idea for a robot that will skateboard?
- Should I say the truth or make a nice story?
- [Derek] Tell us the truth.
- Yeah, so we went hiking and we saw
about 10 people going down the mountain on a skateboard.
And then we thought, wow, this is really cool.
What if we try our robots to make it do this?
So we went to the first shop and we bought a skateboard.
We modified it and we tried it and it worked.
- [Derek] So do you think it allows the robot
to save energy by riding on a skateboard?
- It's more efficient because it uses the legs less.
The legs are basically used to steer,
and then it's just the propellors
that are used to accelerate the skateboard
forward and backwards.
So yeah, it makes it save a bit more energy.
- The propellors of course, make it possible
to skateboard backwards.
Something I struggled with.
It definitely would help if I had a propeller.
(woman chattering)
But the real challenge was slacklining.
(upbeat latino dance music)
This looks incredibly unstable.
So I think this proves the point of just like,
how important control systems are.
You can tell from the footage I have no idea what I'm doing.
(Derek shrieks)
All right, I thought I would be slightly better at that.
Let's give it another shot.
Okay.
Can anyone slackline?
Oh!
This is impossible.
I need a robot to do this for me.
(upbeat latino dance music)
(robot whirring)
I like the sidestepping technique.
Maybe I should have been doing that.
Kind of like copy his technique.
I tried to get some tips by watching Leonardo.
(robot whirring)
But improvement was negligible.
I should've prepared.
You might think it's cheating to use propellers,
but the robot is clearly not flying.
It is supporting itself mostly using the rope,
and it's able to stabilize itself
even with the wild bouncing.
- So human professional slack liner,
- 对于专业的走绳表演者
you can see some of their videos,
你会发现他们在视频中
actually they use arms stretched
会把手臂展平
and then they can balance themselves.
以维持平衡
We don't have the arms for LEO yet.
我们还没给 LEO 安装两臂
We are planning to add a manipulation
我们打算为它安装机械臂
so that he can actually carry some object.
这样它就能拿点什么东西
But in the meantime, we are using the propellers
而目前我们在用螺旋桨
to stabilize LEO while he's actually
让 LEO 在走绳时
walking on a slackline.
保持稳定
- It's funny because like the robot feels like
这些机器人行走或飞行的方式
it's got kind of a personality to it.
好像通人性
The way it walks and flies.
这挺有趣的
It's just totally something you're not used to seeing.
这仅仅是你还不习惯所见的东西
- It looks natural.
- 它看起来很自然
Actually, I have to say that the sensors
实际上 这些传感器
are sampled at 1,000 times per second,
每秒采样 1000 次
but the controller is actually being recomputed
但是无论传输什么信号
whatever signal you are sending
螺旋桨和腿关节的控制系统
to propellers and the leg joints is 200 times per second.
每秒计算 200 次
So it's pretty fast computation.
所以说它其实算得很快
- [Derek] 200 times a second it is adjusting what it's doing
- 它用每秒 200 次的频率规划动作
to maintain balance?
来保持平衡
- Yes, especially propeller control signal.
- 是的 特别是螺旋桨的控制信号
- How does that compare to humans?
- 与人类相比如何
- Oh, humans.
- 呵 人类
So humans can do very sophisticated tasks,
人类能够胜任相当繁杂的任务
but in terms of a fast reaction, it's a very crude machine.
但是在快速反应这方面 人类并不是那么精密的机器
So humans, overall, has a few seconds of delay.
总体而言 人类反应会有数秒的延迟
Time delay.
在时间上
- Is this why I was struggling on the slackline?
- 这是我在扁带上挣扎的原因吗
- Maybe, but...
- 也许 但是
- [Derek] How do you feel about the performance here today?
- 你觉得今天表现它如何
- Yeah, I think it beat you.
- 是的 我觉得它比你强
- I mean, not that that's hard,
我不是说那个 走绳很难
but this is very impressive.
但它的表现让人印象深刻
If you imagine a robot like LEONARDO in the future,
想象一下未来像这样的机器人
like the greatest LEONARDO you could make,
比方说能造出最大的 LEONARDO
what woluld that robot look like and do?
它会长什么样 它能做什么
- So definitely having a LEO-like robot in space,
- 如果把像 LEO 这样的机器人部署在太空
that would be amazing.
一定非常炫酷
But of course, depending on where you go,
但是当然 取决于工作环境
you might not be able to use propellers.
螺旋桨可能派不上用场
So then you would need to use thrusters.
这样就得用推进器了
- So eventually, yes.
- 所以 最后 的确
We want to develop this leg-based adaptive landing gear,
我们想要开发这种基于机械腿的自适应着陆装置
and then we give that to next generation Mars helicopter,
然后我们会把它用于下一代火星直升机
or next generation flying cars
或是次世代飞行汽车
so that it can actually land
它能在极具挑战性的环境中
in very challenging conditions.
着陆
- And still move around once-
- 并且能在四处活动 只要
- And then once, yeah, once you land,
- 是的 只要着陆之后
then you can walk over.
就能到处走动
- Imagine if you have a cliff and then you have the robot
- 想象一下前面有处悬崖 然后机器人
just jump out of the cliff, deploy the propellers and fly.
只要纵身一跃 就启动螺旋桨飞行通过
- [Derek] That'd be wild.
真是太狂野了